All right.
So welcome back to Garys Economics.
Today, we are going to explain why Jeff Bezos
wants to cut your taxes.
Interesting one this week.
We're going to go over to the US,
our surprisingly tall little brother,
which is a country I've not looked at too much recently.
For a bit of context,
the Tax the Super Rich movement has been growing a lot
in basically how much public attention
it's been receiving in the US for a couple of reasons.
Number one, they have a big vote on a
tax on the super rich in California
coming up in November.
And number 2,
Zohran Mamdani has become mayor of New York,
and he's aggressively trying to tax the rich,
including bringing in a tax on unoccupied second homes
in New York City.
And this has really brought a lot of spotlight
to the idea of tax the rich in the US.
There's going to be a vote in November,
and a lot of people including the American
very rich are not happy about it.
And Jeff Bezos, who is the world's fourth richest man
with a wealth approximately about $280 billion,
did an interview for CNBC this week
where he kind of argued that we shouldn't tax the rich.
It's been talked about a lot in the press,
especially over in the US.
It's a really good opportunity
for us to look at what Jeff Bezos is saying,
understand why he is saying it,
and basically understand,
like, where we are at the moment in the kind of
global fight against inequality for a fairer tax system,
for fairer taxation of the super rich,
what our strengths are, what our weaknesses are,
how it's being attacked, and basically how
we need to be smart and what we need to understand
in order to get that fairer tax system that we need.
Okay, so let's jump straight into the interview.
Now, the headline moment was Jeff Bezos arguing
that people on average salaries should pay less tax.
Yeah I, you know, I started thinking about this
and doing some research.
A nurse in Queens who makes $75,000 a year pays 12...
more than $12,000 a year in taxes.
Does that really make sense?
Some people talk about, making the tax system
more progressive.
How about we start
by having the nurse in Queens not pay taxes?
Why are some...
At all.
Why is a nurse in Queens who makes $75,000
a year paying more than $1,000 a month in taxes?
That's $1,000 a month
that could help with rent or groceries or anything.
Okay,
so at the first glimpse, this might seem interesting.
Why do we have a billionaire
arguing for ordinary people to pay lower taxes?
These are...
At the cur-
At the moment, we have a tax system
where billionaires pay very low taxes,
almost nothing, and ordinary people pay,
if you add up all of their taxes,
close to 50%.
So it's a great tax system balanced in favor
of Jeff Bezos and other billionaires,
but he's saying ordinary people should pay less tax.
Okay, interesting, perhaps surprising.
Why is he saying that?
Really the answer is very, very simple.
In order to know that, we just simply need to see
the question that he was answering.
So here is the question that Jeff Bezos was asked,
and his response was cut taxes on teachers.
But one of the topics that I thought we should talk
about, and maybe even start with- Yeah- is these days
it feels almost impossible to pick up a newspaper
without reading a headline about wealth in America,
about the billionaire class,
about wealth inequality and policy
and everything else.
And it's taken a uniquely critical turn, I think.
And I'm so curious,
before we even get into everything else,
what you think about that right now?
Okay, so the question was,
quite, delivered in quite a roundabout way by CNBC.
Basically,
everybody's talking about taxing the super rich.
You are super rich.
What do you think about it?
And that is the question,
in response to which Jeff Bezos eventually
got round to saying, "I think that ordinary teachers
should pay less tax." now if we first analyse this,
from an economic perspective, at a surface level,
this is, like, quite a, like, strange argument, right?
Because just at its most basic, you...
So Jeff Bezos very intentionally picked a,
a salary level, $75,000 a year,
which is quite close to the American average.
You, the average man or woman paying less taxes,
is just quite obviously not a substitute
for billionaires paying more taxes, right?
Like, if we're in a situation
where government needs more tax money
and Jeff Bezos says, "How about instead of that,
we charge ordinary workers less tax money,"
that doesn't solve the problem of tax money, right?
This is a bit like you and I go to a restaurant,
and you know that I'm, like, loaded because you've,
been reading the Daily Mail,
and you are, like, struggling for money.
And you say at the end of the meal,
"Hey, listen, you know, how about maybe,
you know, you cover this one?"
And I say, "Listen, forget about that.
I've got a better idea.
I'm not going to pay for it.
But how about you don't pay for it?" Like, this is...
it doesn't really...
Especially in the UK context where,
government finances are quite stretched,
but increasingly US finances
are quite stretched as well.
The US has a large, and a large deficit and a large
and rapidly growing debt and borrowing costs
in the US are rising like they are here.
It doesn't...
It's a strange argument, right?
It's a strange argument to say,
"Okay, well, tax money is needed,
so instead of me paying more,
how about you pay less?" And it would be easy...
And before I made this video, I watched a lot of...
There's been a lot of US media about this,
and a lot of people
kind of like ******** on Jeff Bezos a little bit.
But I think it would be easy to dismiss this as like,
well, this is like a dumb argument,
especially if you're viewing it from the UK perspective,
because we had, just a few years ago,
we had a Prime Minister, Liz Truss, who basically came
in, like, with this tax strategy of what
we're going to do is we're going to cut tax on billionaires,
and we're going to use that to cut tax on working people.
And what happened is, like, it basically immediately
it caused, like, an enormous economic crisis.
This is not,
a fully fleshed out economic argument.
But I think it's a bit rash
to immediately disregard it because I think,
to a degree, it is an intelligent argument from a kind
of like a rhetorical, like a persuasive perspective for,
like, a very simple reason, right?
So Jeff Bezos, when he,
made this argument, he used a lot of numbers.
And numbers catch people's attention,
especially when they are amounts of money.
And Jeff Bezos, he hits this number,
$75,000 a teacher in Queens earning $75,000,
which is a little bit above the American average,
which means $75,000 will be quite close to the salary
of a lot of Americans who watch this video.
And as soon as they hear that,
they'll be like, "Oh, that's somebody similar to me,
similar financial situation to me." And then he says,
we didn't show this in the clip, but he says,
they're paying $12,000 a year taxes.
That's like $1,000 a month in taxes,
and they could use that money to pay their bills or,
or to pay their rent
or, to take care of their family.
And what he's doing there is he's using
the persuasive power of money, and he's saying,
"Well, listen, if you come with me,
you can get this $1,000 a month,
and wouldn't that be great?
Wouldn't it be great
if you could have $1,000 a month?" And
he's contrasting that to what seems to many people
to be a kind of abstract concept, like...
And he's trying
to make it seem like you have this, like, dichotomy.
Like, you have this choice.
You have 2 things you can choose from.
You can either choose
more taxes for me, Jeff Bezos, and he says specifically
in this interview, "That's not going to...
That doesn't solve anything.
That's not going to help you."
Or what we could have is less tax for you,
$1,000 every single month in your pocket.
And obviously as I've said,
like, you don't need to dig far into it before
you realise, like, this is, this is not...
Just not taxing anyone
is not a really at all a feasible economic strategy.
But, we live in a world where people,
for better or worse,
are a little bit obsessed with money.
We live in a society which obsessed with money.
We live in an economy where a lot of people
are struggling for money, and if this guy turns around
and says, "Look, these guys are trying to tax me,
but we have an alternative, which is to give
every single one of you $1,000 a month," it's going to be,
like, potentially quite persuasive, right?
And when I saw it, it shouldn't be funny
because it's, like, a really serious issue
and, my whole channel is about this.
But it is quite...
What made me laugh
about this is it immediately reminded me of like,
this is how you distract, like, a child or a baby
who is doing something that you don't like.
You say to them,
"Hey, look, do you want to use the iPad?
Do you want to get some ice cream?"
You just switch
the conversation immediately away
from something you don't want the child to do.
"Don't tax me." And he said, "Well, if you do
what I want, I'll give you $1,000 a month."
And of course, Jeff Bezos knows,
he's probably not going to get this policy
that he's demanding.
But it doesn't matter because all he's trying to do
is just distract you away from the thing
that he doesn't want you to talk about
by giving you this, alluring thing here.
Like a thou- Who doesn't want $1,000 a month?
That would be, fantastic, basically.
And it takes advantage
of, a lack of basically economics understanding.
And I think this is the reason why
I try so hard to create a public that just
has a basic understanding of basic economic ideas.
I've done videos
in the last couple of years.
I did one saying, like, "Forget about money."
And the big idea for the forget about money video
was forget about money because money's confusing.
And the government can print money,
and it can do a lot of things.
But what the government can't print is resources.
And at any given amount of time,
there's a certain amount of resources.
There's a certain amount of housing,
a certain amount of energy,
a certain amount of raw materials,
a certain amount of transport, a certain number of cars,
and these will be distributed in a certain way.
And when you understand that, you realise that this idea
that Jeff Bezos is suggesting, "How about you let
me keep my money, and then I will give you more money,"
is, like, kind of like a nonsense.
We can't just
suddenly create more money, Jeff Bezos gets more money,
and you get more money.
But I think it will appeal to some people.
It's taking advantage of,
a lack of economic understanding,
this idea that...
There's an American movie from a few years
ago called Idiocracy, which I actually tried to watch,
and I didn't think it was actually a great movie.
But there's a great scene where,
there's a guy running to be president,
and he says, "Well, what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to give everybody more money."
And he takes that sort of like machine gun.
He starts firing money into the audience.
Because of course we can print out money.
But at the end of the day,
there is competition for real resources.
We exist in economies
where billionaires pay very low rates of tax.
Jeff Bezos himself has paid...
If you look at his life, he's worth about $280 billion.
He's paid, I think, something like $8 billion of tax,
which means on his lifetime income,
he's paid something like 3%
on his whole lifetime income.
You're paying 50%.
His class is getting aggressively richer.
Your class is getting aggressively poorer.
You don't know these things,
and he's saying, "Listen, come with me.
I'll get richer, and you'll get richer."
And what this plays on is basically the fact
that we all hate tax, we all hate politicians,
we all hate the media, and we're looking
for somebody else who's going to save us, right?
And I think this reminds me very much of basically what,
what Elon Musk does and what Donald Trump does,
where they portray themselves as, "I'm not a politician.
I'm a businessman.
I know how to make money.
Come with me.
I'll get rich.
I'll make you rich." And I think it would be too much
to simply dismiss this, right?
These guys, what they're trying to do
is portray themselves as the sensible guys in the room,
the guys who are smarter than the politicians.
And really, they're kind of fishing.
This is like $1,000 on the end of a hook,
and they're hoping that you will bite that,
and you will accept a system
which is aggressively impoverishing you.
So when I see this,
what it tells me is that obviously here in the UK,
the voice of the wealth tax movement is me.
And I run...
I am, a financial trader, and I run
essentially this economics educational channel.
And everything I do is about educating the public that
if you don't want to get poorer, you have to tax the rich.
But in other countries like the US,
where I'm not such a well-known voice,
a lot of the argument has been about fairness,
has been about justice.
And it is vulnerable to basically somebody who is
a billionaire coming in and saying, "No, ignore that.
These guys are not talking about how to make you rich.
I will make you rich." So I think the next thing
you should recognise when you see this argument of let's
not tax me more, let's tax working people less,
is, I think it highlights a little bit the stupidity,
in a way, of the way we discuss tax in the media,
which is we talk about we should tax these people more,
these people less.
And sometimes we talk about spending.
We should do more of this spending,
or we should do less of that spending,
without realising that these things have to be funded,
essentially.
And people are only really able to come out
with these sort of ridiculous suggestions
like let's just tax everybody less because
we don't connect the tax side and the spending side.
And obviously there is also the option
of borrowing more, but... or even printing money.
But whenever you say we should cut taxes,
you need to be clear,
okay, where is that going to come from?
Where is the money going to come from,
basically, in whichever way.
And this is why from a couple of years ago now
we've really been pushing the, tax wealth,
not work message.
Because even in this country,
I think that from very, very early on,
because people don't really understand the difference
between, a billionaire and, which is...
A billion is just an insane amount of money.
It's like it's really not in any way
realistically attainable to an ordinary person.
Whereas a million is still maybe something you could get
if you manage to get a good job
or if you inherit a house from your parents.
They use this confusion
between a billionaire and a millionaire such that
when somebody like me or somebody like Gabriel Zucman
or somebody like Zoran Mandani
or Zach Polansky says increase tax on the very rich,
they want you to think we're trying to tax you.
And it's this classic bait and switch that when I say,
"Tax the super rich more,"
they say, "Watch out for Gary.
He's trying to tax you more."
And that is why I've been really aggressively focusing
on this, like, tax wealth, not work message.
Now, tax wealth, not work is,
although it's extremely concisely summarised,
it is a coherent economic message
because we take some money from this group,
and we give that money to this group,
and it's, balanced from a government perspective.
What Jeff Bezos is suggesting, which is tax me less
and tax you less, it raises the obvious question of,
where does that money come from?
What Jeff Bezos actually said was,
"Should we tax you more?" And he's like, "Shh.
Don't talk about that.
Let's tax the viewer less." And he's doing this thing
which I often do in my interviews,
which is when I'm being interviewed by someone
who is maybe a bit of a ********,
which happens sometimes, rather than debate
the interviewer, who is often debating me in bad faith,
jump over the interviewer, go to the audience and say,
"Listen, I'm the one who is on your side," basically.
And Jeff Bezos is doing this.
But it has the obvious weakness
of where does the money come from?
And the interviewer picks it up and says,
"Okay, well, you want to tax ordinary people less.
How about we fund that by taxing you more?"
Should you be paying higher taxes
to pay for the 3% component part of this
that you think is going to need to be paid for,
if not more than that, given the debts we have?
It's certainly,
a perfectly valid policy debate
to say, do we want an even more progressive tax system?
So, the kind of the line that gets,
quoted all the time is,
the wealthy should pay their fair share.
Right.
And we can argue about what the fair share is.
That's a policy debate.
That's okay.
We actually have a spending problem,
And that's a skills issue.
Let me give you an example.
The New York City school system.
Right.
They spend $44,000 per student.
44,000.
That's 30% more per student
than other big cities like Chicago,
LA, and Boston.
If we ran Amazon
the way New York City runs their school system,
your packages would take 6 weeks to arrive.
We'd have to charge you $100 delivery fee,
and then when the package did finally arrive,
it'd have the wrong item in it anyway.
So this is Jeff Bezos's next argument, which is...
It's kind of the shallowness of his first argument,
which is like, "Hey, let's just not tax anyone," is exposed
pretty quickly that was...
I don't think you'll find any economist
that say this is really feasible.
Just don't tax anyone.
You'll struggle to find that working anywhere.
So if you want to cut taxes on workers,
which is what Jeff Bezos is really pushing,
maybe we should tax you more, you - Jeff Bezos.
And then Jeff Bezos again throws the ball away.
It's another distraction, which is
no, actually, the real problem is a spending problem.
And he uses this term, which he uses, I think he uses it
7 times in the whole interview, which is skills.
He says it's it's a skills issue.
And now he's moved the argument on to something
which is, at least in theory,
more economically feasible.
So his first argument is, okay, should we tax you more?
And he's like, "How about we tax working people less?"
And that's nice.
It's bait for working people
because working people want to pay less tax.
But, it really is not economically complete
because we can't just start taxing everybody less
unless we want to do austerity.
And in countries like the UK where
we've seen austerity, that's been incredibly painful.
So then he says, "Okay, okay.
We can tax working people less without taxing you more
by cutting government spending." And he kind of floats
this idea that government spending at the moment is,
is wasteful, it's inefficient.
I'm really interested
in his repeated use of this term skills issue,
which I'll get into a little bit more later.
And once again, what you have is an argument
which on the surface is appealing.
And the reason that it's appealing
is because everyone hates government.
It's becoming more and more widely,
accepted in public opinion that politicians are
********* and that governments are wasteful.
So,
yeah,
of course, we want to reduce government
waste, and we want to increase government efficiency,
and we want to improve government skills.
So, yeah, great argument, Jeff Bezos.
Who's going to disagree with you?
And I think this,
this in itself is the weakness of the argument.
If you suggest that
the way to fix something is to do something
which absolutely everybody in the country wants to do,
then you're probably not offering anything
particularly of value, right?
Like, I think, the population of the UK
is 66 million.
You'd struggle to find,
50 people who don't think
we should reduce government waste, and who don't think
we should increase government efficiency,
and
who don't think we should increase government skills.
And it's the same in the US.
Every single politician ever has come in saying,
"We're going to fix this problem
by decreasing government waste
and improving government efficiency." So if
that was a thing that you could quite simply just do,
given that absolutely everybody in the whole world wants
to do it, we would have already done it by now, right?
And it's... it's meaningless, but it's popular.
So once again, what you see here is Jeff Bezos using,
kind of weaponising, I guess, in a way,
a lack of broad economic understanding in the public.
So in the first case,
he offers something which is, not really possible,
which is "How about nobody pays tax?
And then everybody will be rich."
Which is great because everybody hates tax.
And then he says, "Well, how about we just,
make the government efficient
because the government is, rubbish.
And I'm Jeff Bezos, and I will give my skills
to the government." And this is popular
because government is, really hated.
And what he's trying to do here
is basically set up an alternative,
boogeyman to himself and the billionaires,
which is government is ****, taxes is ****.
And, this is, in many ways,
a good persuasive argument
because the boogeyman you are creating
is somebody who is already hated.
Everybody hates government, and everybody hates taxes.
And it's quite funny because another thing
which Jeff Bezos says early in the interview is,
politicians are...
They're using this age-old technique
of, picking a villain and pointing fingers.
But the problem is that doesn't solve anything.
So Jeff Bezos is asked early on in the interview,
"Should rich people pay tax?" And he basically says,
"You know, these guys are pointing their fingers at me
and the billionaires, and it's saying my fault.
It's my fault.
But look, pointing fingers doesn't solve anything.
Basically, what you need to do is,
replace the government because the government
are rubbish, and you should get rid of taxes
because taxes are rubbish."
Which is pointing the fingers in a way
that doesn't solve anything because the two things
which you have suggested are one thing
which is impossible, which is to cut taxes on everybody
without reducing government services,
and another thing which absolutely
everybody ever has agreed with and tried to do
and failed, which is to reduce government inefficiency.
If I step back and I look at what has happened on the,
whatever you want to call it, a tax the rich movement
or the, the anti-inequality movement
or the wealth tax movement in the last,
2 years,
5 years, 10 years. If you'd have told me
10 years ago or 5 years ago or 2 years ago
we would be where we are now, where this issue is,
constantly one of the big issues
in politics when the economy is discussed,
where, billionaires like Jeff Bezos
would feel like they have to reply on it,
where we're getting wealth taxes all over the world,
even in countries which have right-wing governments,
I wouldn't have believed you.
But I think the one thing which I've been trying
to provide, which we don't have enough of
in other wealth tax movements around the world,
is this clear, simple economic message.
Which is the reason your living standards are falling
is because of growing inequality,
and I think that is made clear by Jeff Bezos
saying exactly that in this interview,
that taxing me doesn't solve anything.
It's not going to help that nurse in
Queens.
We need to make the case that it does.
We need to make the case that it will.
And really, the whole story
of the history of this channel is me sort of every week
trying to make that case in a different way.
I think if you want one simple video
that you need to watch on this channel
to understand why growing inequality is
what is hitting living standards,
I would recommend watching the video from last year
called The Squeeze Out, which basically explains that,
once you stop taxing rich people
at high rates, which we did in the '80s,
they start to generate an enormous amount of income.
They start to buy up the assets.
They get richer.
Asset prices go up more and more.
Ordinary people can't afford to buy assets anymore.
And eventually you see wealth ownership,
the ability to own, squeezed out of the working class
and squeezed out of governments.
And then obviously people have nothing left,
and they start to see their living standards fall.
I think that is the best video we've made
that explains the economic case.
And Jeff Bezos
himself is an excellent example, right?
So Jeff Bezos is, if Google can be trusted,
worth about $280 million.
[Jack] Billion.
Sorry, yeah, thanks.
Jeff Bezos...
I made the mistake myself there.
Jeff Bezos is worth $280 billion,
which means that if he makes 5% a year,
which he'll almost certainly make significantly
more than that, he's going to make $14 billion a year,
which is something like $1 billion every 4 weeks.
So he's making, $250 million a week,
so he's making, like, 30 or $40 million a day.
Really,
if you want to understand why having untaxed billionaires
hurts your living standards, you don't really need
to understand anything more than that.
Once you have a class
of people making 30 or $40 million a day...
Imagine you're making $40 million a day.
How much would you spend?
I couldn't even imagine spending,
$100,000 a day.
Okay, so let's assume you spend $100,000 a day,
and then you've got another,
you've still got another,
$28 million still, to spend.
You have no choice
but to slowly buy all of the assets in the entire world.
That is what is going to happen,
and that is exactly what is happening.
And then what that means is other groups of society
will lose their ownership of assets, and we will
eventually end up in the kind of extremely unequal world
that we have been in.
So the...
This is the point that I want you to understand
as much as you can.
The growing wealth of the billionaire class
is the reason that you are getting poorer.
This is the reason you can't afford a house.
It's the reason your government wealth is collapsing.
These two things are the same thing.
You cannot have one tiny minority of people that own
everything and not have everybody else owning nothing.
So I think this...
A lot of people have been ******** on Bezos
this week, and I think it was kind of...
I think his intervention was ultimately kind of dumb,
and I think it will be self-defeating.
But he's highlighted one really important thing.
We need to, as much as possible,
clarify, simplify, make clear the economic reasons
why allowing the billionaires to be untaxed and to own
everything will and is making ordinary people poorer.
And I want to finish on one last bit of sort of,
business jargon which Jeff Bezos taught me.
So what did he say after he said,
Amazon could fix this?
If we have a problem at Amazon,
the way we would fix it is we would go in,
and we'd do the 5 whys,
and we'd try to get to a root cause.
We try to find a root fix.
And then when we fix it at the root,
you're fixing it forever.
So did what the 5 whys are?
The 5 whys... I had to look it up.
The 5 whys is basically this idea.
You have a problem,
and... I find it interesting as well.
Basically, you just keep asking why,
why, why until you find the reason,
which is once again, exactly like what kids do.
Jeff Bezos, a lot of similarities to a young child,
it seems.
So let's get into this, all right?
Let's get into these 5 whys.
Why can't you afford to buy a house?
What is the reason?
Why is that happening?
The answer to that,
I think, is because you are increasingly competing
with a class of unbelievably rich people
who are making $30 million every single day
for the ownership of the assets in the world.
If you look at the countries
and the places in history
where housing is affordable, they are countries
that do not have incredibly wealthy billionaire classes.
Like Europe in the
period after the World War II.
And if you look at the countries
where housing is unaffordable,
like now, these are places
where you have these super wealthy billionaires.
They're buying everything.
Of course they're buying everything.
It's not just housing that's getting expensive.
Assets in general are becoming expensive
because you're competing with billionaires.
Okay, but the 5 whys...
Okay, we keep asking.
Okay, well, why?
Why do we have a super, super wealthy billionaire
class now when we didn't have that in the '50s and the
'60s and the '70s and the '80s and the
'90s when housing was much more affordable?
Well, the answer is quite simply because in the
'80s we stopped taxing billionaires effectively.
We used to have very high rates of tax.
In the golden age of capitalism, after World War II,
we had incredibly high rates of tax on the rich.
In this country, I think we had 95% top income tax,
90% top inheritance tax
on the very rich. And
what that meant was rich people like Jeff Bezos
were not able to do this thing
where you have an enormous amount of income
and you just reinvest it and reinvest it
and reinvest it, and you get compound interest,
and it grows exponentially,
and eventually I own the whole ******* world.
Okay, so why did that happen?
Why did we stop taxing the super rich in the '80s?
The answer was because we lost an argument
about tax and inequality and distribution.
And people like Margaret Thatcher
and Ronald Reagan managed to convince the public
that not taxing billionaires would be good for them.
And why did that happen?
Because, quite simply, we forgot the thing which
our grandparents and great-grandparents
and great-great-grandparents understood,
which was that distribution and inequality matters.
It's as simple as that.
And I've said it time and time again.
If we have an intelligent,
educated public that understand one simple thing,
which is that if you allow inequality to grow rapidly,
it will hurt living standards,
then we will be 70, 80, 90% towards winning this battle.
And I think that that is where we need to be.
Whether you're here in the UK or in the US,
giving all your money to Jeff Bezos,
or in Germany, or in Australia, or in France,
or in Italy, or Spain, or any of these countries,
we need to be in a situation where if you go outside
and pull your average man or woman off the street
and say, "Why are living standards falling?"
the answer that the majority of them give you is
because inequality is rising.
Once we get to that situation,
then we will be able to fix this problem.
That is your answer to Jeff Bezos's 5 whys.
And the truth is, and I almost don't believe
myself saying this we're getting there.
We're getting there.
We're getting there all around the world.
Here in the UK,
and I'll talk about this some more next week,
we're going to get a new prime minister.
It could be as soon as the next couple of months.
It might take a year.
But when that new prime minister comes in,
they will really, really, really, really struggle to
win the confidence of the public unless
they deliver something on inequality.
And the reason for that is quite simply
because the British public understands now
that if you don't act on inequality,
their living standards will fall.
And I've been all across the world,
in the last year or so.
I've been... obviously Australia, New Zealand.
We had Gabriel Zucman here from France last week.
But I've been to Italy and Portugal
and Sweden and Norway, and people are starting
to understand this all over the world.
And we are reaching a situation where when even a
right-wing government, comes in,
in Hungary,
they have no choice but to take action on inequality.
And, I think it's amazing
the progress that we've made.
But the fact that Bezos feels that he can come out on TV
and say, "Taxing me is not going to help you," shows
that we have more distance to go.
We need to make that clear message
for the public to understand of course it affects us.
Of course it affects us.
If we allow a class like you to own everything,
then we will go back
to where we were in Europe 300, 400, 500 years ago,
where the whole ******* world is owned by,
like,
20 guys, and the rest of us live in desperate poverty.
This is part of the foundation of America,
this idea that you cannot have,
this all of the wealth owned by a few people.
But also, when I see Jeff Bezos come out,
it gives me hope, to be honest.
Because,
when I first started working
on inequality, 2011 is when I first started work on it,
and nobody was interested in this.
And we've been pushing it, we've been pushing it,
people like me and Gabriel Zucman,
but also the guys, so many different people
all across the world that have done great work on this.
It reaches the point now where the fourth
richest man in the world, feels like he needs
to go on ******* YouTube and chat a load of bullshit
to fight people like us to fight people like you,
to stop you from getting your fair share of the pie.
And there's this famous quote,
which is probably not a real quote,
which is, "First they ignore you,
then they laugh at you, then they fight you,
then you win." And I've been doing this work
for 15 years now, and the truth is I was ignored
for probably about 12 and a half of those years.
And
even if you look at, I mention it so often,
but when
Zach Polansky went on The Rest is Politics,
and they pointed him and laughed at him essentially
and said, "What are talking about?
You're an idiot.
There's no economists,"
And then we go and pull out 7 Nobel Prize-winning
economists, and Gabriel Zucman from France
and say, "Listen, we've got them.
We've got the economists." We're winning.
Jeff Bezos is a very wealthy man,
and he's not going to waste his time
and his money buying newspapers and coming out on TV,
and arguing he shouldn't be taxed
unless we were winning.
We've forced them into this.
And when I see these guys coming out
and, putting themselves on the front lines,
kind of stupidly, to be honest Jeff Bezos trying
to make himself the voice on
opposing wealth taxes I think is kind of stupid.
But it shows them
that we've got them backed into a corner here.
And I didn't believe this
for years and years and years and years and years.
But the fact is, I do think we're going to win.
I do think we're going to win.
But we can't be complacent.
When Jeff Bezos comes out and makes those arguments,
we do need to understand
that some people are going to listen to that.
We cannot let the billionaires
be the voice of aspiration.
Listen, if you look at countries where
people have been able to go from poverty to being rich,
these were not countries
which had aggressively growing inequality.
If you allow your country to be a country
where the poor get poorer every year and
the rich get richer every year, that will not be a world
where ordinary people like you
can get into being financially secure.
We need to move away from an economic system
where wealth is being drained away from the many
and accumulated by the super rich,
and towards an economic system
where wealth circulates around.
But listen, the rich are getting richer.
They'll buy themself a lot of newspapers
and a lot of media channels, and they'll put a lot of,
silly videos on the internet.
What we need is an educated public
that understands one simple message:
if we allow inequality
to get worse and worse and worse, then you and your kids
and your grandkids will be living in poverty.
So in answer to Jeff Bezos, it will make a difference.
If we tax the super rich, it will make a difference.
That is the only way that we can get wealth back
in the hands of working people, and that is the only way
that you and your kids can be rich.
Tax Wealth Not Work, thank you very much.